Welcome back. In this video,
we'll discuss how to tell a
powerful story using data.
We'll teach you how to
gather and organize
your project data
to present it to
others within your organization.
Presenting is a powerful
way to communicate
your ideas and support
your decisions throughout
the project journey.
Think of presenting as telling
the story of your project.
Storytelling is the
process of turning facts
into narrative to communicate
something to your audience.
Storytelling is how you
bring data to life
and is a useful way to
tell stakeholders within
your organization
about your project.
In a way, we're all
storytellers using
information and experiences
to share ideas with others.
Stories usually have a
beginning, middle, and end.
To tell a great story using data,
we'll go over some best
practices to make sure
your story is complete,
accurate, and compelling.
In general, there are six
main steps to storytelling.
First, define your audience.
Then, collect the data.
Next, filter and
analyze the data.
Fourth, choose a
visual representation.
Then, shape the story.
And finally, gather
your feedback.
Now let's review each one.
Step 1: define your audience.
In this first step,
it's important to know
who you're presenting to.
Are you presenting
to project sponsors
or executives? Or
to team members?
Define your audience and find
out what matters most to them.
Begin by asking yourself
qualifying questions like:
What would my audience want
to know about the project?
Or, what are their
most urgent concerns?
Which key data points
influence the story
and project outcome?
This will set you up to know
the type of story you want to
tell and the type of data
you should use to tell it.
For example, years ago,
I was working on a
project for Google Maps.
Our goal was to apply a label to
every business in the
world: restaurants,
hotels, gas stations—you
name it.
There are many, many,
many businesses in the world,
and I only had a small team
of engineers to work with.
For this project, we
tailored our storytelling to
an audience of vice presidents
from Google Maps and Google Search.
Both were important to consider,
because we were
helping users find and
connect to businesses through
the Google Maps app and
through Google Search.
I'll return to this
example as I take
you through the steps
of storytelling.
Next step is Step 2:
Find the data that connects to
the question you want to answer.
You'll need to begin
searching for data from
trustworthy resources to support
the point you're trying to make.
Leverage the relevant
project resources
in documents like
your project plan or
work management software to
download and analyze
key data points.
For my Google Maps project,
the question we were
trying to answer was:
Where should we focus
our attention first?
So to find the right
data for this question,
we turned to the many businesses
in our internal database and
the available information
about what types
of businesses users
were searching for.
That brings us to Step 3:
Filter and analyze the data.
Now that you've
collected your data,
you'll need to vet it for
credibility and filter
the information.
For my Maps project,
we used search queries to
determine the types of
businesses that users
searched for most often,
which included restaurants,
cafes, and hotels.
There were other categories—gas stations,
museums, etc.—but
they collectively made up
a much smaller percentage of
geo-specific search traffic.
Step 4: Choose a
visual representation.
Visualizations are a great
way to help people remember
the information
you're presenting and
are an essential piece
of storytelling.
You can use data in
different ways to tell
a story, like using dashboards,
charts, infographics,
and mappings,
and we'll go over these examples
in more detail in the next video.
For my Maps project,
we decided on a pie chart
to help tell our story,
which brings me to Step
5: Shape the story.
After you've analyzed
your data and
know how you'd like
to visualize it,
it's time to tie it all together
into one cohesive narrative.
Take some time to think about
what you're hoping to achieve,
the points you want to make,
and the questions and
concerns you want to answer.
For the Maps project,
we used the pie
chart to show that
most geo-specific
search queries are
covered by a relatively
small number of businesses.
So we built a story
about that data.
We wanted agreement from our
VPs to work on improving
the data behind this set of
categories in a
few major markets.
It needed to illustrate that
if we improved the category data,
we'd succeed in improving
the search results for
more than 50% of geo searches.
Lastly is Step 6:
Gather your feedback.
Similar to how you
may ask a friend
to practice with you
before an interview,
you want to be sure that
before you present,
you do a trial run.
Try getting feedback from someone
who's not connected
to the project.
Find out if it was interesting.
Did it make sense? What
questions did they have?
Their feedback can help you
identify areas of
your story that were
unclear or unmemorable and
give you a final chance
to make adjustments.
To recap, you want to define
your audience, collect the data,
filter and analyze the data,
choose a visual representation,
shape the story, and finally,
gather your feedback.
The key to effective
storytelling is to be
organized, intentional,
and prepared.
Coming up, we'll talk
more about Step 4:
effective visualization.
See you there.